<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Account of the late earthquake in Jamaica, June the 7th, 1692 written by a reverend divine there to his friend in London ; with some improvement thereof by another hand.</title>
            <author>Reverend divine.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25348</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10440535</idno>
  <idno type="VID">45038</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240863239</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing A308_VARIANT</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28170</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">10440535</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25348)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45038)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1392:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Account of the late earthquake in Jamaica, June the 7th, 1692 written by a reverend divine there to his friend in London ; with some improvement thereof by another hand.</title>
                  <author>Reverend divine.</author>
                  <author>H. L.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface signed: H.L.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Earthquakes --  Jamaica --  Ethical aspects.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Maria Cecilia Caride </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Maria Cecilia Caride</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45038:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45038:1"/>
            <p>ACCOUNT OF THE Late Earthquake IN JAMAICA, <hi>June</hi> the 7th. 1692.</p>
            <p>Written by a Reverend Divine there to his Friend in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With some Improvement thereof by another Hand.</p>
            <q>Watch ye therefore, (for you know not when the Master of the House cometh, at Even, or at Midnight, or at the Cock-crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or in the Morning) Least coming suddenly, he find you sleeping — And what I say unto you I say unto all, Watch —
<bibl>
                  <hi>13 Mark 35, 36, 37.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurst,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>three Crowns</hi> at the lower End of <hi>Cheapside,</hi> near <hi>Mercers Chappel.</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:45038:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45038:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HEre is (I think) the fullest Account of the Amazing severity of God towards <hi>Jamaica</hi> in their suprizing Earthquake, that has yet been given us: And thô it be many Months since the first Effects of it appear'd in that Island, and the News of it first reach'd us, yet it's not fit (I conceive) that this Relation of it (which lately came over) should be conceal'd, and lye buried in unprinted Privacy; and that for these Reasons:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> The Dreadfulness of the matter of Fact requires that it should be declar'd abroad; to the Inhabitants of that Isle has the Lord spoke terrible things in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness: His sudden Judgments there have destroy'd many, astonish'd all; their Streets have quickly been swallowed up by the gaping Earth; their Houses over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd, the Inhabitants have either gone down quick in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Pit, or been cast floating upon the Waters; the
<pb facs="tcp:45038:3"/>numbers of their corrupted Dead has almost kill'd the Living; their Mountains have been cleft asunder, or dashed one against the other; some of the People have been almost pin'd with Thirst, while others fear'd the Sea would overwhelm the Island: Is it not necessary then that we should know what God has done to them, that we may hear the Voice of his Rod, and fear and forsake our Transgressions?</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> That from this dreadful Story we may learn Thankfulness to God: Has <hi>London</hi> already forgot what fright and amazement it was cast into this last Summer by reason of an Earthquake? Whether the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cussion at <hi>Jamaica,</hi> and that here was one Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake or no, yet we should stand and admire the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguishing Mercy of God: Are we spared to hear of the doleful Judgments in <hi>Jamaica?</hi> Are we alive, and preserved from an Earthquake here, to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand how many are slain by it in that Plantation? We are only jogg'd, that we may be awaken'd from our Security; they are surprized in their deadly sleep, and hurried away to endless Death: Let these Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of the Lord excite in us grateful resentments of his forbearance and Long-suffering towards us: Why is not <hi>England</hi> like to <hi>Jamaica,</hi> and our Metropolis like to <hi>Port-Royal?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> The Quality of the Relator may justly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the History to publick perusal; 'tis penn'd by
<pb facs="tcp:45038:3"/>a Reverend Divine who is now in the Plantation, and has long been seated there; One who with a tender sense of Gods Displeasure, felt the Trepidati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Island, an Eye-witness of the direful ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the Earthquake, and one that has full oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of informing himself by others of what he has not seen; one that in the very writing of this Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative knew not how soon he might be in the case of the Inhabitants of St. <hi>Jago de la Vega,</hi> and therefore writes as in the presence of that God whose Power he had seen and felt; one that writes, as not knowing but that he might quickly be Entomb'd in the opened Earth, and go down into silence with his Pen in his hand: One who writes to á dear Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and therefore could have no design to deceive; one whose Integrity would not suffer him to seek any sinister End: And thô his Account may seem to come late, yet therefore it may be supposed to be the more full, and the longer it staid for Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the more credible Testimony it brings along with it. Therefore,</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> This Narrative may serve for Prevention or Discovery of false Reports that may be spread abroad concerning this stupendious Disaster; some perhaps out of good meaning may aggravate the Calamity, in order to signalize the Judgments of God; and some (as the Reverend Author observes) may serve their
<pb facs="tcp:45038:4"/>own ends in representing the Case worse than it is; and others may carry on malicious Designs, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring by an amusing Story (as if the whole Island were destroy'd) to discourage Merchants from Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thither, which would indeed advance their suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings greatly, and increase the Desolation the Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake has made.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> Since the Author has been so gratefull to God, so ingenuous as to recount the remaining Mercies of the Place, as well as faithful in rehearsing Gods Judgments there, tells us what they enjoy, as well as what they want, it may be (and we hope it will be) that hence all due care may be taken for their speedy and constant supply with such things as are necessary for 'em in a state of Peace or War; since their strongest Houses are demolish'd, their Arms broken, their great Dependency (as to Visible Means) the Town of <hi>Port-Royal</hi> destroy'd, their Fleets lacera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and their Spirits quaking as well as their Isle, they may justly fear the forcible Invasion of the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous <hi>French,</hi> or Insurrection of Domestick Slaves: Therefore we hope they will be (if they are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready) assisted and furnished with Men, Arms and Ammunition for their speedy Defence and Protection. And since their Staple-business goes on, since <hi>Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten</hi>'s, <hi>Indigo</hi>'s, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are in Preparation for the Market, and their <hi>Sugar-works</hi> employ'd, let Pious
<pb facs="tcp:45038:4"/>Merchants especially hasten to fetch their Goods, and to carry things necessary for the Plantation: So may they reap advantage to themselves, and shew Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to the Distressed Island; The Kindness they Exhibit to the poor Inhabitants may quickly be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd with Interest into their own Bosoms. Blessed are the Merciful, for they shall Obtain Mercy.</p>
            <p>On these Considerations, who can but Conclude, that the Publication of this Letter (for so it is) may be very Usefull. And since the things <hi>Printed</hi> in the <hi>Volume</hi> of Divine Creation and Providence, as well as those <hi>written</hi> in the <hi>Inspired Records,</hi> are for <hi>our Learning,</hi> I shall at the End of this Narrative subjoyn a few <hi>Corollaries</hi> for our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction and Notice.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H.L.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:45038:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45038:5"/>
            <head>The Truest and Largest ACCOUNT OF THE <hi>Late Earthquake</hi> IN JAMAICA, <hi>June</hi> the 7<seg rend="sup">th.</seg> 1692.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <q rend="margQuotes">
               <p>WAving all other Private and Particular Concerns at this time, give me leave to present you with an Account of a late dismal Calamity and Judgment, which hath befall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en us here in this Countrey by a Terrible Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, which a just God hath sent upon us on <hi>Tues<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> the 7th. of <hi>June,</hi> about a quarter of an Hour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Eleven of the Clock, and continued with great Violence and Terror, (as most say, about one Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45038:6"/>of an Hour) but in my Opinion not above six or seven Minutes; in which time it overthrew all the Brick and Stone Buildings in the Countrey, whereof several in my own Parish, which now are either levelled with the ground, or standing Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Wrath of God, are so shattered and torn that they are irrepairable: While these were tumbling, the Earth opened in my Parish in multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of places, and through their dire Chasms spew'd out Water to a considerable heighth above ground, in such quantities in some places, that it made our Gullies run on a suddain, tho' before ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding dry; insomuch that some were afraid of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing overwhelmed at once by the River and Sea join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together to swallow up the Countrey, these gaping Mouths being no less than 12, 20, or more Foot deep under the Earth, and above two Miles up in the Countrey, especially nigh the River, in the purest Mould, which had not Clay or other Conso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidating Matter beneath to oppose the force of the Fountains of the Deep breaking up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for where that was, we do not find any Cracks of the Earth at all; and yet it pleases God that we in this Parish have escaped the Danger much better than our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Parishes; for happening to Content our selves with mean and low-built Houses, for the most-part built with Timber, and boarded, or with Cratches set deep in the Ground, and Plaistered, such Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses are generally standing: So that we have Means to assist one another in this calamitous distress: While from the other parts of the Island we have no less true than fearful Relations, of hundreds of Souls cast out of their Dwellings, and not a Place to hide their heads in, except what they have since built, Booths or Tents, to shade themselves from the Sun.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:45038:6"/>
               <p>Our noted Town of St. <hi>Jago de la Vega,</hi> or <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish Town,</hi> is utterly down to the ground, with its Church devoured in the same Ruines. Our Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeen and only Store house of <hi>Port-Royal</hi> is three parts swallowed in the Sea, Ships and Shallops now riding at Anchor where great numbers of fine Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricks have been not long since; the Relation of which single Places Sufferings to give you in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, would not only weary your Eyes, but make your Heart ake to read it; many very eminent Merchants, before worth thousands, are now scarce worth more than the blew Linnen on their backs; several are dead, either overwhelmed with their Houses, or drowned in the Sea, which flowed in suddenly upon them; while they fled from the Sea, the Earth devoured them in her gaping Jaws, or they were knockt on the head with the Houses fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on them, and while they fled from the gaping Chasms of the Earth, or the tottering Buildings, the Sea met them and swept them away. A whole street, (which we call the <hi>Wharf,</hi> where most of the noted Merchants lived, and where much of the Planters Goods was Landed for convenience of Sail and Shipping, (more especially Sugar and Cotron) sunk at once from one end to the other, with a general crack at the very beginning of the Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, together with two Forts, Guns, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> built thereupon; and which is more dreadful, all those poor Wretches perished that were either upon, or nigh it, without any Warning; and presently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this, while the People were in the greatest Horror and Consternation imaginable, neither ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving time to fly, or thoughts where to fly for safety, two or three more streets in their whole length tot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered and fell, and were immediately sunk, Land
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45038:7"/>and all together deep into the Sea, as far as the <hi>Jews</hi> street: All the upper part of the Town, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Church, and all above towards the Pallisadoes, is under Water, even their Pallisadoes it self where their Burying place was, is now no longer Earth, but Sea, and (ghastly to behold) the very dead Corps that were there submerged (I may say) instead of Inhumed, even at their Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals floated from thence to all parts of the Harbour.</p>
               <p>Such Houses as do yet remain, are from the <hi>Jews</hi> street, and backward, to that we call the great Sea side, but many of them so rent and torn, others so deeply sunk into the Water, whereof some as high even as the Balconies, that they are unser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable; the Wall at <hi>Pallisadaes</hi> is utterly ruined, with the Port thereto belonging; and tho' <hi>Morgans line,</hi> (which stands the best of all) the principal Fort, (and as they say) <hi>Walker</hi>'s Fort, do yet stand, yet they are sorely shaken and rent, and so sunk, they are not tenable; the whole place that is yet above water, sinking daily by those Earthquakes we have ever since had, sometimes four, five, or six times, more or less, in four and twenty hours, I my self expecting now while I am writing, when the Earth will tremble under me, thô in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts of the Countrey I have not heard or seen any farther damage done by any Earthquake that hath followed the first; for which Mercy we have great cause to Bless God even in our Misery, who only so frequently puts us in mind of what he hath so lately done, and can yet do what he will with us at his pleasure. The reputed number of the Dead, according to the general estimation (for perhaps there will never be any true Account) is commonly reckoned at fifteen hundred persons,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45038:7"/>besides Blacks, who 'tis probable may be six or se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven hundred more, a multitude of whose Corps floated a great many days after from one side of the Harbor to the other, which caused such an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable stench, that the Dead were like to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy the Living, till at last some were sunk, others disperss'd by the Sea-breeze, some to one place, some to another, upon the Keys to the Leeward of the place, some even fall'n down as far as the Outbounds of my Parish, which is many Leagues from <hi>Port Royal,</hi> where they lye unburied upon the Rocks and Sands as they were cast up.</p>
               <p>Immediately upon the Cessation of the extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Earthquake, your Heart would abhorr to hear of the Depredations, Robberies, and Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences that were in an instant committed upon the Place by the vilest and basest of the People; no Man could call any thing his own, for they that were strongest, and most wicked seized what they pleased, and whose they pleased, and where they pleased, without any regard to Propriety. Gold and Silver, Jewels, Plate, or Goods was all their own that they could or would lay hands on: No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but breaking open of Houses, rushing into Shops, and taking what they pleased before the Owners faces, forcing Goods or Money from them in the open street, as they were carrying it else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where for better Security, succeeded the Horrors of this dreadful time; while others in Canoo's, Wherries, Ship-boats, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were plundering Chests, Boxes, Screwtores, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of what they could find in them upon the Water, even the very Slaves thought it their time of Liberty, wherein they committed many barbarous Insolencies and Robberies, till they were suppress'd by the Death of some, and punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45038:8"/>of others. Many days did these Depredati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons last, especially upon the Water, where the Dead were robbed of what they had about them, some stript, others searched, their Pockets pick'd, their Fingers cut off for their Rings, their Gold Buttons taken out of their Shirts, and then they were turned adrift again; from thence was taken all manner of Stores that would swim, every one taking that for his own which he could lay his hands on, as Pork, Beef, Mackril, Salt-fish, Coaca, Candles, Soap, Wine, Beer, Brandy, and a vast deal of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, not here to be thought of, or reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up; and tho' our Council (for our Governour is dead) have published a Proclamation, That all manner of Goods, Money, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> so seized, as by way of Prize upon the Water, shall be accounted for by the present Possessors unto such Persons throughout the Island, as are by Proclamation ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and for Encouragement thereunto, they are allowed the third of the whole Prize; or if they do not return in an account of what is in their possession by such a time, they are to be proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed against as Thieves and Robbers according to Law; yet by the present Proceedings of some who are reputed to have most of such Prize-goods in their hands, it seems that much of it will never be discovered; much of it is certainly damaged and spoiled, and other of it will be in others possession, and that by the Consent of the Owners themselves: So that the richest are now the poorest, and the meanest of the People are now enriched by the Los<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of others, which Loss duely to Estimate and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, is perhaps more difficult than to reckon the number of the People lost.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Port-Royal</hi> in its flourishing Condition, was a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45038:8"/>Empory and Mart Town for these <hi>Indies,</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were brought partly by a private, and partly by a publick and allowed Traffique (the <hi>Achiento</hi> being settled here) a very large share for so small a place of the Riches of <hi>Peru</hi> and <hi>Mexico,</hi> which not only enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our Merchants and Factors here, but whereof yearly were Transported for <hi>England</hi> in Coin and Bullion vast Summs; so that 'tis not to be compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted what is lost, but many People think at least to the Value of 400000 <hi>l.</hi> at <hi>Port Royal</hi> only, of which the Merchants at home will bear the greater share, which when you hear what 'tis there, you may perhaps give as good a guess as our selves. — You would admire at the Goodness of God in the Preservation of the residue; some were very mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culously delivered from Death, swallowed down in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Bowels of the Earth alive and spewed up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and saved by the violent Eruption of Water through those Gaps; some (as they say themselves, if they were alive at that time to know what was done to them) were swallowed up in one place, and by the rushing of Waters too and fro by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the agitation of the Earth at that time, were cast up again by another Chasm at places far distant. But the general Means of Preservation was by Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples flying as fast as they could toward the back Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side, or getting aboard the Ships in the Harbour by one means or other with all speed possible, which were presently crouded with Men, Women and Children, and among which our Man of War, <hi>The Swallow,</hi> then in the Harbour, and Careening close by the Wharf, was so damnified by the Fall of the Houses, that upon View since she is condemned as unfit for future Service; and Capt. <hi>Cunning</hi>'s Ship being a Merchant-man of some Force, is made our
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45038:9"/>Guard-ship, himself being ashore and buried in the ruins. Besides this, 12 Shalops are sunk that lay within the reach of danger, and further Damage at Sea I do not hear of any.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Port Royal</hi> being thus ruined, and utterly despair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of being a place of Safety for Habitation, it is intended utterly to be deserted, most people believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that in a few Months it will either be all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Water by reason of its daily sinking, or at least but a very small remnant or Riffe of that narrow Neck of Land will shew it self after a while: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Council have very lately agreed upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, called <hi>The Rack,</hi> whereon to build a Town for the Reception and Accommodation of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, which is within the same Harbour as the other, but some Leagues farther up in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, at the farther end of the Haven, whereunto an approved of Channel leads, and which is not only more safe for Shipping both against Enemies and Storms, but is described also to be very nigh, and with very little Labour may be made altogether as convenient as the famous Harbour of <hi>Port Royal;</hi> it being Capable (now as Nature framed it) to receive Ships of the greatest Burden very nigh to the shore, which may be much advantaged in a small time by the building of Wharfs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the Benefit of lading and unlading of Ships, as at <hi>Port Royal</hi> before. From thence it is but a short way to <hi>Ligania,</hi> the first and principal place for Plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (whereunto my own Parish is immediately the next) which for the most part imitating, if not exceeding the stateliness of <hi>Port Royal,</hi> is now the more terribly brought to Desolation, together with its fine New Built and not yet finished Church, buried in the same Ruines with the Houses; above
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45038:9"/>which Place the lofty blew Mountains lift up their Heads, but are now so rent and torn that they are fearful to behold, and are like to stand for lasting Marks of the Wrath of God, which hath also hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in other parts of the Countrey, it being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Mountainous in the middle part, insomuch that by the Fall of a Mountain into the Channel of the River which supplies both the Town and <hi>Port Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> with Water, the River became dry for sixteen Hours together, to the Amazement of the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, fearing the Desertion as well as Desolation of the place, 'till it afterwards run again as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly; and they were informed of the Cause of the stoppage of the Water for so long a time. This among other Reasons was the Cause why the People that were saved at <hi>Port Royal</hi> were almost perish'd for Thirst in their deep Extremity, their own Water-Casks being either ruined or swam a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way into the Sea, or no Boats to fetch any in that deep Consternation, or otherwise imploy'd to save People's Lives, or to get Plunder; or if any did go, there was no Water to be had, so that as it was hard to be gotten, so it was dear, and many paid great rates only to quench their Thirst. And yet for all these great Disasters, great Numbers of People are not at all reformed of their Wickedness, which brought this upon us, but there is the same Whoring and Drinking, the same Cursing and Swearing, if not worse than formerly; so that we may fear the Judgment of <hi>Sodom</hi> will be the next Punishment you will hear of.</p>
               <p>For my part, I desire to fear and Adore that terrible Majesty that hath wrought such Terrors among us, all the days of my Life; and however many People at <hi>Port-Royal</hi> may be given up to a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45038:10"/>Reprobate Sense, whom neither the Mercies of God, nor yet his Judgments can bring to Repentance, yet I hope this hath been an effectual Warning to many of us in the Countrey, who knowing the Terrors of the Lord, will for the future be the more easily perswaded to an amendment of Life. I que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion not but there are many Petty-factors at <hi>Port-Royal,</hi> who have stated their Accounts, and bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanced their Books with the sole Answer of an Earthquake, whose Interest therefore it is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>present it in the most dreadful manner possible, that they themselves may seem the more excuse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to their Employers, as if the whole Island were destroyed thereby, which will discourage Merchants from Trafficking hither, and will be a means of further suffering thereby. Yet as I have done my best to give you a true Information hitherto, so I can assure you of the Truth of what I farther as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert. That by the Blessing of God having hitherto reasonable good Weather, the Planters continue em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd in making of Goods, Cottons, and Indigo's, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> providing them for a Market; and such who have Sugar works, which is the staple of the Island, many of them had Timber buildings, which are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther little or not at all prejudiced; and others who built with Brick, or Stone, have so much time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween this and Crop-time, that they can, and doubtless will fit themselves in some measure in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to it: So that I am sufficiently convinced, and therefore would perswade any other, that whoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Trades hither for any manner of Goods for Cloathing, Houshold-stuff, Arms and Ammuniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (which are generally spoiled) all manner of Provisions, Plantation Utensils, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> will come by so much to the better Market, by how much they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45038:10"/>hasten to our Assistance, and need never fear the freighting of their Ships homeward, there being a present damp upon Trade, which I don't know how long it may continue, so that we shall have great quantities of Goods ready for them, to dispatch them the sooner away. God in his Displeasure remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred Mercy, and therefore this Calamity happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Day-time, to the safety of many hundred Souls; for though such Numbers perisht at <hi>Port Royal,</hi> where they were thronged together in an Istmus of Land, yet I cannot hear of fifty Persons, both Whites and Blacks, that perished throughout all the Island beside. — And though in the midst of our distress it pleas'd God to give us a signal Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory over our Enemies, the <hi>French,</hi> who happened at that time to make the sharpest Attack upon us since the War, having landed some say 200, some say 80 Men at the North-side, which is but weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly furnished with Men, where they intrench'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, but were shamefully beaten out by a vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous On-set in the Night, by a Party of about thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Men, who slew 7 or 8 outright, and the rest fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Boats were 30 of them drowned, while in the mean time our Fleet which was set out on purpose pursuing theirs, we took one Shalop, and made them desperately blow up their great Ship; such as were saved remaining our Prisoners, and others fled home to give an Account of their Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw. What may be the effect of these sad times, God only knows: Our first Fears were concerning our Slaves, those Irreconcilable and yet Intestine Enemies of ours, who are no otherwise our Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects than as the Whip makes them; who seeing our strongest Houses demolisht, our Arms broken, and hearing of the destruction of our greatest De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45038:11"/>the Town of <hi>Port Royal,</hi> might in hopes of Liberty be stirred up to rise in Rebellion against us, which is a War always the more terrible, by how much there is no Quarter given in it, but they kill and slay all the Whites, Men, Women and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, that they can Conquer; but God be praised these sears begin to be blown over. The next Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequence is either Famine or great and extream scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, which it is true we do not feel yet, nor may not this six Weeks, yet if it should please God to withhold his Rain from us, (as it hath often happened of late Years about this time; and I never heard of an Earthquake as a Sign of good Weather,) we must certainly very shortly languish under that dire Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; or if it please God in Mercy to remember us in Misery, and to give us the former and the latter Rain in its Season, yet the least that we can suffer will be an extream Scarcity of all manner of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, <hi>Port Royal</hi> our Store-house being destroyed, in which much of the Provisions are either sunk or spoiled in the Ruines, or floated away to Sea no one knows whither, or damaged, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Another Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequence we fear is the forcible Invasion of our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, now our Hearts are low, our Arms broken, our Forts Lacerated and useless, our main stay and support sunk under Water; (though God be Prais<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our Magazeen of Powder in <hi>Port-Royal</hi> be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) the Men that should have been the Strength of the Island, many hundreds of them drowned, yet do we not dread so much what Mischief our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours here can do us, tho' at this time they may do us mischief enough, with reference to particular Persons that are adjacent to the Sea-shores, but are not able of themselves to ruine the Island; only that which we most dread, least the King of <hi>France</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:45038:11"/>upon this News should send hither an Army to Invade us, to prevent which our whole Trust and Confidence under God is in his Majesty, who is him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self Lord and Proprietor hereof in his own Person, and therefore we hope for some speedy Relief from him; in Order whereunto the Council have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spatcht a Shalop to him the 22<hi>d.</hi> or 23<hi>d.</hi> Instant, to give him an Account of our Present Condition, and to request his speedy help, and which we all hope he will not be backward in, towards an Island that in its flourishing State brought in very considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Revenues into his Exchequer; an Island that hath made a Notable Figure in these parts of the World, and which himself and his Predecessors have dignified with the Government of very Noble Peers, and yet which may be now ruined in our low Estate by a few Slights or Neglects. I am weary now of recounting our Miseries to you, which I have done in a Style as tho' you knew all the Places I have mentioned to you; but tho' you don't, others into whose Hands it may fall, may. I have done with the Account, yet not with my Letter, until I add this sincere Assertion, that I am on all Accounts</p>
            </q>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Jamaica. <hi>Withywood</hi> in the Parish of <hi>Vere.</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>June</hi> 30th. 1692.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>SIR, </salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours</hi> —</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="commentary">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:45038:12"/>
            <p>Thus we have heard what has befallen this <hi>Ameri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi> Plantation, what wonderful Signatures of Divine Displeasure have appeared there. Let Apocalyptick Divines make what use of this Earthquake they shall judge meet for the unfolding of any Portion of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetick Scripture, we shall only from this Relation deduce a few Remarks of General Use and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then, Since <hi>God's Judgments are abroad in the Earth, let the Inhabitants of the World learn Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness:</hi> Isa. 26.9. The World's Inhabitants should not only learn Righteousness, when they themselves are under the lashes of God's chastizing Rod, but when others are so too; when Judgments are in the Earth, in any Nation or part of the Earth, those that see and hear of 'em, should hear the Rod, and who hath appointed it. The Lord in this Alarming Act of his speaks not to <hi>Jamaica</hi> or <hi>America</hi> only, but to us also: He calls aloud to us to consider what he has done there, that we may acknowledge his terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Majesty, and sin no more against him: Had we had no awaking Experience of his mighty Power here, yet the certain Account of what he has done elsewhere, should mind us of our Duty, least their Case should become ours; which Duty seems emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently included in the word <hi>Righteousness,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, even all that to which we are <hi>obliged</hi> by <hi>Rules</hi> of <hi>Equity</hi> and <hi>Justice,</hi> or should be <hi>inclined</hi> to by a <hi>Principle</hi> of Mercy and Compassion; that we now learn to give unto God the things that are His, and unto Man what belongs unto him; which is more largely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd by the Prophet, <hi>Micah</hi> 6.8. <hi>He hath shewed thee, O Man, what is good, and what does the Lord require of thee, but to do justly, love mercy, and walk humbly with
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45038:12"/>thy God:</hi> v. 9. <hi>For this the Lord's voice cryeth unto the City, and therefore the Man of Wisdom</hi> (he who has <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Senses exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cised to discern both Good and Evil) should in these things <hi>see God's Name;</hi> should read the lively Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters of his Power, Wisdom and Righteousness, the bright discovery of his Glorious Excellence.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let those whose <hi>Hearts are set in 'em to do Evil, know that Sentence is sometimes executed speedily.</hi> The Lord is slow to Anger, but he will not retain his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience for ever; those whom his Goodness leads not to Repentance, shall feel that abused Mercy will end in the most dreadful Sentence: Hardned Wretches are apt to encourage themselves in their Villanies by reason of the Impunity of the Wicked; Alas, they consider not that Life at longest is but short, and then an Eternity ensues, which is long enough to punish profligate Sinners in; yea, and even that short Life is sometimes shortned by God's immediate stroke, and the Criminal is sometimes apprehended in his Act of Sin, and forthwith hurried unto Execution; See, and trembling see here Sentence executed in few minutes upon above 2000 Persons at once: I say not that all these who fell in this Common Ruine pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished everlastingly; but as they all thrô Sin de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served thus to Dye, so Death was in a short time inflicted on 'em all. <hi>Who shall not fear thee, O Lord, and Glorifie thy Name? for thou only art Holy; let all Nations come and worship before thee, for thy Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are made manifest,</hi> Rev. 15.4. Therefore,</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Let Atheistical Spirits seasonably learn that there is a God that judgeth in the Earth:</hi> An Omnipotent Supream Being; one who, as Omnipotent, Disposes and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rules the whole Visible Creation; as Supream, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penses Favours or Afflictions to whom he pleases;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:45038:13"/>One, who as Almighty, can, and sometimes does pervert Nature's long known byass: As Soveraign Lord of all, saves or destroys whom he will: One who by his Power causes the Water to spring out of dry Ground, who enlarges the ancient bounds he has set unto the Sea, makes the Earth to tremble, the Mountains to drop down with fear, when he's dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleased: One whose Soveraignty and Dominion is <hi>Absolute</hi> and <hi>Ʋniversal,</hi> and therefore may dispose of all things at his own pleasure, accountable to none: One to whom the Lives of all Men are forfeited by Sin, and therefore may execute his threatned Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments when, where, on whom he will; tho as Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute Proprietor of Rational things, as well as of all other, he might take away Life and Happiness: yet as he gives Law to us, by which we must be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated, so he deals not meerly Arbitrarily with the World; has revealed rules by which he himself will proceed in distribution of Calamities and Benefits: At the General Day of Account, all shall be judged according to the Law they knew, and all the mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries here that they undergo are <hi>Judgments,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the just Execution of a Righteous Threatning, the deserved fruit of their own Sin; and tho' God (as an offended Legislator) may take away forfeited Life and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness from all transgressing Creatures, yet in his judging the Earth he leaves evident footsteps of his Supremacy and Lordship: At the same time that he (as just Judge) punishes some, He (as Gracious Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactor) spares, delivers, and defends others, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps no less guilty than the punished. Who has made the Astonishing Discriminations in the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of late? Why is not <hi>England</hi> in the ruinous Case of <hi>Italy?</hi> or <hi>Rotterdam</hi> like to St. <hi>Jago?</hi> Did blind chance make that Visible Difference among the dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45038:13"/>of <hi>Jamaica?</hi> Did Chance kill the 2000, and save the preserved? Did that unlock the Bowels of the Earth, to swallow down many alive, and cast 'em up alive at a distance, while others sunk down to be no more seen, or not till they were Dead? He that can think Chance, or any thing else, without th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perintendency of a Wise, Powerful, Righteous being, is the Cause of these Discriminations, must needs be as unreasonable as an Atheist.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Let the Reader of this Account consider, whether it does not render much of the History of the Old Testament very credible:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <bibl>2 Thes. 3.2</bibl>
               </note> There are some Unbelieving (who are also <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>illogical, unreasonable</hi>) Men, that laugh when they hear of the dividing of the Red Sea, the opening of the Rock for the <hi>Israelites</hi> to drink, and other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances of Divine Power; but let 'em consider what was done in this Island: Is not cleaving the Hills by a boisterous Vapour, as difficult as parting the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters by the Wind? Is not the gaping of the Earth, and out of its Chasms spouting floods of Water aloft into the Air, very near a kin to the loosing of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter out of the Rock? That Persons sunk down into Caverns of the Earth, should be cast up again <hi>Alive</hi> by the Eruption of Water, is so stupendious, that it may rationally induce us more easily to believe the safe Conduct of the <hi>Israelites</hi> thro' the Red Sea; and other prodigious Particulars here, tho' they don't parallel <hi>Mosaick Miracles,</hi> yet may be admitted as <hi>Motives</hi> of <hi>Credibility,</hi> and may incline us to think, that he that can effect these things, could work those also.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Let us see here the destructive Consequents of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending the Lord of Hosts, the Creator, Proprietary, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45038:14"/>Ruler of the Ʋniverse: The Soul that sinneth, it shall die,</hi> is his established Law, which we see every Day exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted on one Transgressor or another; the Graves are every day laying up some or others, but Death comes sometimes and sweeps away shoals along with it at once; sometimes in the shape of a Plague it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solates Cities and Countries; sometimes armed with an Earthquake, it transports whole streets of Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants on a sudden to another World: Two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand at once slain in <hi>Jamaica!</hi> and scarce had time to gasp out a Prayer for their departing Souls! O Tremendous Judgment! O cruel Sin! And shall we still provoke this Holy Lord God, whose Judgments warn the World to cast off all Impiety in haste, lest Iniquity prove its ruine? Shall we still shut our eyes against the evident light of such clear Admonitions? Shall we deafen our Ears against the loud voice of such instructing Examples?</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Let Atheistick Scoffers now be silent, no longer ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject against the promise of our Lord's Coming; nor plead, that since the Fathers fell asleep, all things continue as they were from the beginning of the Creation.</hi> What great alterations does our Lord frequently make in the World, to tell us that all these things must be changed, and that he is a coming? With what Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders is Nature one where or other often disturbed, to put us in mind that the whole visible System of Heaven and Earth will e're long be dissolved? How <hi>Beauteous</hi> and <hi>Canonical</hi> was the whole Fabrick of the World at its first Creation, when all things were very good, consormable to the Creators Will? when all Creatures knew their Places, Use and End: I mean, when all things according to their Natures and Capacities answered the End of their Creation;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45038:14"/>when the inferior Beings served Man, and according to their abilities promoted his De light and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; when Man was purely free from all inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to, and act of transgressing his heavenly Fathers Commands: There is indeed much Exactness and Regularity still in the Universal Frame, but how har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious may we suppose it to be before the least Disorder or Confusion had <hi>untuned</hi> any part of it? then the whole was indeed a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>beautiful structure;</hi> and the Noble parts of it indeed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Poems, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act, symmetrical</hi> Composures; or in the words of the Heroick Poet,
<q>
                  <l>The Parts to <hi>number,</hi> and fix'd <hi>Rules</hi> were brought,
<note place="margin">
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Cowley</hi>'s Davideis.</bibl>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>By the Eternal Mind's <hi>Poetick</hi> Thought;</l>
                  <l>Water and Air He for the <hi>Tenor</hi> chose,</l>
                  <l>Earth made the <hi>Base,</hi> the <hi>Treble</hi> Flame <hi>arose,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To th' Active Moon a <hi>Quick brisk stroke</hi> he gave,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Saturn</hi>'s string a <hi>Touch</hi> more <hi>soft</hi> and <hi>grave,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Motions <hi>streight</hi> and <hi>round,</hi> and <hi>swift</hi> and <hi>slow,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>short</hi> and <hi>long,</hi> were mixt and woven so,</l>
                  <l>Did in such <hi>Artful Figures</hi> smoothly fall,</l>
                  <l>As made this Decent Measur'd <hi>Dance</hi> of <hi>all.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But how is the Dance now confus'd? The Poem since that how stript of its Rhime and Measure? and the whole Composure how ravel'd and distorted? Sea and Land exchanging places, the Fetters of the Ocean unloos'd, Mountains either pluck'd up by the roots, or their Branches lopt off, Spouts of Water bursting out of the divided Earth, Cities interr'd with their Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, the Sea become a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Church-yard; the Earth cast into Convulsive Paroxisms, in <hi>America, Italy, France, Holland</hi> and <hi>England;</hi> were not these <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Earthquakes in divers places,</hi> foretold by
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:45038:15"/>our Lord, together with <hi>Wars and Rumors of Wars;</hi> since then we find his Word verified in these things, let all be excited to believe the Promise of his Come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Nay, was there not in this <hi>American Island</hi> a short representation of the great Day of Tryal? Hills shaking and rending asunder, the ground reeling un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the tottering Inhabitants, and casting up the Dead it had swallow'd; the Sea too exposing its Dead on Rocks and Sands to open View, People running to hide themselves from Common Destruction, Hearts aking, Faces appal'd, Outcries and hideous Shrieks terrifying those that were safe; and has not our Lord told us it will be so at his return? Let us Watch and Pray that we may be found of him in Peace.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Learn the Necessity of Effectual Grace for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of the Mind and Heart:</hi> Bare Convictions will not do, the sight of unusual Judgments will not do, the tearing of the Earth we tread on, the beholding of others hastily snatch'd out of the World, the fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Expectations of sudden Death, the visible effects of Sin upon others, the lashes of our own Consciences in time of Danger, will not effect so great a Change, without the powerful concurrence of the Holy Ghost. Surely here was <hi>(moralis Suasio)</hi> Perswasive Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment enough to prevail with the People of this Island to hate <hi>Sin</hi> as long as they lived, which had been attended and pursued by such direful effects; surely one would have thought the terror of this quaking day would have left a perpetual impression upon their Spirits, and have been a continual Goad to incite 'em to fear that God, who by <hi>doing such Wonders</hi> had demonstrated himself <hi>Glorious in Holiness;</hi> should they not now have examined their State and Relation to another World, and resolved henceforth
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45038:15"/>to live in constant thoughts of Death, and prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for future Judgment? On the contrary, we find 'em in the time of great Danger, under the power of an hardned Heart, and inflexible Obstinacy in Sin: No sooner were the apprehensions of common Ruine worn off their Spirits, but all outragious Villanies dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered the fixt perverseness of their Hearts; <hi>Imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately upon the Cessation of the Extremity, your Heart would abhorr</hi> (as our Author says) <hi>to hear of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>predations, Robberies and Violences that were in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant committed upon the place; Gold and Silver, Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, Plate or Goods were all their own who would, or could lay hands on 'em.</hi> Desperate Sin and Madness! Could they not see the avenging Power of God? Would they not consider the Operation of his hands? Yea, since these deplorable Disasters; <hi>There is</hi> (as our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor complains) <hi>the same Whoring and Drinking, the same Cursing and Swearing, if not worse than formerly.</hi> O aggravated Impieties! so that the Reverend Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor fears that the Judgment of <hi>Sodom</hi> will be the next Punishment: Or perhaps God may no more punish them so openly, but let 'em perish securely in their Wickedness, as saying, <hi>Why should ye be stric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken any more, ye will revolt more and more:</hi> And are not other Countries lately terrified, as flagitious still as they were before their surprizing Terrors? Does not Sin still Domineer in <hi>Italy,</hi> where 'tis said, Many Cities have been lately overthrown? Yea, does not the <hi>Man of Sin</hi> Tyrannize there? Has <hi>New England</hi> shaken off its wickedness, since its self was shaken? Does not Drunkenness and Sabbath breaking abound as much in lower <hi>Germany</hi> as ever? Has <hi>France</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of, or abstained from Pride, Cruelties, inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Barbarities, and Rapines, since their fearful Trepidations? Nay, has not our <hi>London</hi> too forgot
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45038:16"/>it's Consternation and Amazement? Is not the same Cursing and Swearing, the same Whoring and Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the same prodigious Prophaneness, Contempt of God, his Authority, Power, Laws and Institutions, the same abounding Profligacy as formerly? Is any part of <hi>England</hi> reclaimed, either for what it hath felt or heard?
<note place="margin">
                  <bibl>Isa. 1.4.</bibl>
               </note>
               <hi>Ah! sinful Nation, a People laden with Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, a seed of evil doers, Children that are corrupters, ye have forsaken the Lord, ye have provoked the Holy One of Israel to anger, ye are gone away backward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Let's Observe how God in Wrath remembred Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy:</hi> The Cup of Trembling put into their hands was not unmixt with some Favour and Compassion; the Mercies of the Lord fail'd not, therefore they were not wholly Consumed; <hi>'twas Mercy</hi> that this over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning Earthquake happened in the Day, and not in the Night, when all the Inhabitants were chain'd with sleep: Had it befallen them in the Night, how many Inhabitants had perished which now are safe? in sleep they might have gone down to the Chambers of Death, and so ne're awak'd 'till the Morning, when all the Dead shall arise; they could not have so much Time and Warning to hasten from the gaping Earth and falling Houses, and sinking Streets, as now they had; so that our Author says, <hi>That tho' such Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers perisht at</hi> Port Royal, <hi>where they were thronged to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in an Istmus of Land, yet he can't hear of fifty Persons, both Whites and Blacks, that perished through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the Island besides.</hi> Yea, in the midst of their Distress, when Dread and Confusion seiz'd 'em, when their famous Empory was sunk or sinking, when Arms, Ammunition, and their best outward Defence was gone, then did the Inhumane <hi>French</hi> make the fiercest Attack upon them since the War; as if they had said,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:45038:16"/>
               <hi>We will pursue, We will overtake, We will divide the spoil, Our Lust shall be satisfied upon them, We will draw the Sword, Our hand shall destroy them, for God hath blown with his Wind, the Sea hath covered them, they sink as Lead in the mighty Waters:</hi> But God was pleas'd to shew, that tho' these <hi>Americans</hi> fell into his Hands, yet they should not fall into the Hands of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, for their Mercies are Cruelties. God would shew that he would admit no Competitors or humane Agents in the Inflicting of his Punishments at this time; what was done should be by his own Hand; and therefore he seems Angry with the <hi>French,</hi> who would have made great Accessions to their Sorrows. His Providence in this Case seems audibly to say to them, <hi>I am sore displeased with you that are now at Ease, for I was but a little angry, and ye would help forward the Affliction;</hi> therefore God curb'd their Malice, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strain'd their Power, and gave the <hi>Jamaicans</hi> a Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Victory over them, as the History relates; yea, since their Miseries they have had reasonable good Weather, the Planters continue imploy'd, Cottons and Indigo's, and other Commodities are providing for Sale, their Sugar-works little prejudiced, and what are damnified may be repaired before Crop-time; so that many Benefits remain, thô many are lost; their Magazeen of Powder in <hi>Port-Royal</hi> preserved, thô three parts of the Town are ruin'd, a convenient and safe place yet remains for the building of a New Town to the same Harbour; so that God has not quite for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten to be Gracious to 'em, nor suffer'd his Merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness to fail.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>From the whole Story, let us Contemplate the Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness of those who</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>receive an unshakable Kingdom, a Kingdom that cannot be moved:</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:45038:17"/>We see the Uncertainty and Instability of sublunary things. Political Societies are not immutable; the most extended Empires, most flourishing Monarchies, and best settled Aristocracies, States and Churches, dye and crumble into nothing; Kings are set up and pull'd down, Governments raised or depressed at the beck of the Universal Sovereign; at his Nod too Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures Works forsake their long established Laws, break their settled Peace, start from their wonted Course; unknown Revolutions turn all things upside down;
<q>
                  <l>Et quicquid gremio Lunae complectitur orbis,
<note place="margin">
                        <bibl>Buchan.</bibl>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Permutat, variat{que} vices, trepido{que} tumulta</l>
                  <l>Aestuat, &amp; nunquam sentit pars ulla quietem,</l>
                  <l>Sed ruit in sese, &amp; civili vulnere semper</l>
                  <l>Aut cadit, aut perimit, alio{que} renascitur ore</l>
                  <l>Rursus ut intereat—</l>
               </q> But happy they who are Members of that stable So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, against which the Gates of Hell shall not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, who are the true Subjects of that Kingdom which is ruled and defended by the King Eternal, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal and Invisible, and are related unto the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens and Court of Heaven,
<q>
                  <l>— Nitidi est sublimis Regia coeli</l>
                  <l>Immunis senij, &amp; vultu immutabilis uno</l>
                  <l>Perpetuum servat solida &amp; sincera Tenorem;</l>
               </q> Where are no Commotions of the State, or Concussi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Place; no Disorder in the Government, or Imperfections in the Subjects; no such Vicissitude as that of Day and Night, for they have no need of the Sun, neither of the Moon to shine in it, for the Glory of God doth lighten it, and the Lamb is the Light
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45038:17"/>thereof; and the Gates of it shall not be shut at all by Day, for there shall be no Night there; of what sort soever, and how long soever the Apocalyptick Reign shall be, which Divines so much speak of now a dayes, the faithful Servants of the Lord Jesus shall have their Portion in it: Or if only part of the rais<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Saints shall possess it, the rest shall not want it, as being blessed in Heaven; happy they who unwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riedly seek <hi>that City above, whose builder and maker is God;</hi> who are invested with a Title to, and in some measure <hi>made meet for the Inheritance of the Saints in light; who are come to Mount Zion,</hi> (which no Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake shall reach) <hi>and unto the City of the Living God, the heavenly Jerusalem, and to an innumerable compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Angels, to the General Assembly and Church of the first born, which are written in Heaven, and to God the Judge of all, and to the Spirits of just men made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and to Jesus the Mediator of the New Covenant, and to the blood of sprinkling,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <bibl>Heb: 12.22, 23, 24.</bibl>
               </note>
               <hi>that speaketh better things than that of Abel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Hence let us be perswaded to be entire Followers of the Lamb, who can secure us from the Troubles of the World, and from the Wrath to come;</hi> who gives us now some Demonstrations of his Power and Displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, that we may be quicken'd to prepare for his se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Appearing: If we are his, we shall be safe, tho' the crack'd World should fall to pieces: He reigns still, and will reign 'till he hath trampled all his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies under his Feet: Thô he were dead, yet he's now alive, and lives for the safety of those for whom he dyed, and has Redeemed out of every Nation, and People, and Language; he now exhibits to the World some small dayes of Wrath, as Prologues to, and Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nosticks of that great day of Wrath, when the whole
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:45038:18"/>Globe shall flee in haste from his Presence, even the whole Terrestrial Globe, of which we are now apt to say
<q>
                  <l>— Stat nullo mobilis aevo</l>
                  <l>Terra,
<note place="margin">
                        <bibl>Buchan.</bibl>
                     </note> super solidae nitens fundamina molis</l>
                  <l>Pollenti stabilita manu—</l>
               </q> Not only shall some parts of this lower World start with the Fright of the Judge's Presence, but the vast Ball shall be ready then (if not now) to verifie the <hi>Copernican</hi> Hypothesis, and perhaps shall then become the <hi>primum mobile;</hi> but to be sure, the Graves shall be opened, and the Archangel's Trumpet shall sound to the utmost Corners of the Earth; then the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal shall be fixt, the Books of Records opened, the Criminals summon'd, but shall be found loth to leave their Prisons, shall Wish for a more hideous Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake than that of <hi>Jamaica</hi> to swallow them up quick; shall call to the Mountains to fall on them, and the Hills to cover 'em from the Judge's Face and Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence; but the Mountains shall skip like Rams, and the little Hills like young Sheep; then shall these poor Miscreants be Doom'd to Everlasting Destruction, from the Presence of the Judge and from the Glory of his Power; then shall those that Love the Lord Jesus in sincerity, lift up their Heads with Joy, they shall be openly Acknowledged, Dignified, Crown'd, and instated in the Everlasting Possession of that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable Kingdom, which here they were entitled to. O Dreadfull,
<note place="margin">
                  <bibl>Rev. 22.14</bibl>
               </note> O Joyfull Day! But, <hi>Blessed are they that do his Commandments, that they may have right to the Tree of Life, and may enter in thro' the Gates into the City.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:45038:18"/>
            <head>
               <hi>BOOKS lately Printed for, and Sold by</hi> Thomas Parkhurst, <hi>at the</hi> Bible <hi>and</hi> Three Crowns <hi>at the lower End of</hi> Cheapside, <hi>near</hi> Mercers-Chappel.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>SYnodicon in Gallia Reformata:</hi> Or, the Acts, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cisions, Decrees and Cannons of those Famous National Councils of the Reformed Churches in <hi>France,</hi> being a most Faithful and Impartial History of the Rise, Growth, Perfection, Decay of the Reformation in that Kingdom, with its fatal Catastrophe upon the Revocation of the Edict at <hi>Nants</hi> in the Year 1685. also the Confession of Faith and Discipline of those Churches, their Speeches, Sacred Politicks, Cases of Conscience, and Controversies in Divinity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> their Government, Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Collected out of the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Manuscript Acts of those Renowned Synods. In two Vol. Fol. By <hi>John Quick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Body of Practical Divinity, consisting of above 176 Sermons on the lesser Catechism, Composed by the Reverend Assembly of Divines at <hi>Westminster,</hi> with a Supplement of some Sermons on several Texts of Scripture. By <hi>Thomas Watson,</hi> formerly Minister of St. <hi>Stephens Walbrook, London.</hi> Recommended by se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Ministers to Masters of Families and others. In Folio.</p>
            <p>Theological Discourses and Sermons on several Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions. In two Parts. By <hi>John Wallis,</hi> D. D. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessor of Geometry in <hi>Oxford.</hi> Quarto.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:45038:19"/>
            <p>A short Story of the Rise, Reign and Ruine of the Antinomians, Familists and Libertines, that infected the Churches in <hi>New-England,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>A Brief Tract on the Fourth Commandment, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is shown the Cause of all our Controversies about the Sabbath Day, and the means of reconciling them. Recommended by the Reverend Dr. <hi>Bates</hi> and Mr. <hi>John Howe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached before the King and Queen at <hi>Whitehall, Nov.</hi> 5. 1692. By <hi>Richard</hi> Lord Bishop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sathan sifting, or the Oyl of Joy for the Spirit of Heaviness. In Octavo.</p>
            <p>Death Improved, and Immoderate Sorrow for De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceased Friends and Relations Reproved. By <hi>Edward Bury,</hi> formerly Minister at <hi>Great Bolas</hi> in <hi>Shropshire.</hi> Octavo.</p>
            <p>The Carnality of Religious Contention. In two Sermons Preached at the <hi>Merehants-Lecture</hi> in <hi>Broad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>street.</hi> By <hi>John Howe.</hi> Octavo.</p>
            <p>An Epistolary Discourse on the great Assistances to a Christians Faith, and for a more intire Rest and Assurance in the highest Tryals and Adventures there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; with a second Part upon the Present Times, and these rare Vicissitudes of Providence in the Publick State of <hi>Brittain</hi> in this Age. Dedicated to her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty.</p>
            <p>A Discourse of Earthquakes, as they are Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural and Premonitory Signs to a Nation, with a respect to what hath Occurr'd in this Year 1692. and some special Reflectiuns thereon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> These two last by <hi>R. Fleming,</hi> Minister at <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> Author of <hi>The Fulfilling of Scripture.</hi> Octavo.</p>
            <p>A Paraphrase, on the <hi>Psalms</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> in Metre. By the late Reverend Mr. <hi>Richard Baxter.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:45038:19"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>